[Music]
do
hello everyone good evening good day to
all of you and welcome to the 81st live
episode of ask abhijit
so let me greet all of you who are here
i can see some pretty play with noob
abhishek vinit krishnan
bhushan patel suru um
smith
venkata
fist wizard praful abhishek komal
and lots of other people good evening
good day to all of you it's great to be
back as usual
this fine weekend with all of you
so today i'm gonna take questions that
you have asked in the comments so and
before we go go into that uh i hope you
are enjoying the uh
podcast that i'm putting up on this
channel i have put up so i think four so
far and lots more are coming
so i hope you all are gaining some value
from that you have been listening to me
talk on this channel for hundreds of
hours
so maybe it's time for you to get gain a
different kind of perspective
so the objective of all these podcasts
that i'm putting up that i will be
putting up is to offer you a different
perspective different uh kind of
knowledge
uh
to expose you to different kinds of
people guests from various parts of the
world
and that sort of thing
so that's the reason why i'm doing it
now i see one comment very often and i
understand why it's there so
uh when see typically the podcasts the
discussions conversations are going to
be in english on this channel sometimes
they'll also be in hindi i will
let the guests speak in whatever
language they are most comfortable in so
one of the comments i get is please do
the podcast in this language or that
language if it's in english there's a
request to do it in hindi if it's in
hindi there's a request to do it in
english
so that unfortunately is not going to be
possible i cannot do a podcast in
multiple languages i cannot put up
subtitles it's an enormous amount of
work to do subtitles so it's going to be
as is
my only objective is to offer you the
most exposure to different ideas
different perspectives different people
right
so i hope you gain some value from it do
your best to learn from all these
conversations
i am going to offer them in whatever
language we're going to have the
conversation in and it's going to be as
is
this it's not going to be available in
multiple languages unfortunately it's
not feasible right
so i hope it's providing you some value
and i'm going to bring in uh people that
you may not expect some people i'm sure
you'll be you'll be knowing them and so
i will certainly invite some people that
you may have never heard of before so i
am a very curious person i'm going to
follow my curiosity i'm interested in
all kinds of fields and topics science
geopolitics history culture art all kind
of things so that's what you can expect
going forward right so
so i hope you guys gain some
good value from that
okay now with that said let's get into
the questions
for today let's begin with question one
which is by vishal why couldn't the two
greatest persian empires the achaemenid
empire in the sasanian empire conquer
arabia
all right
so
it's not that they could not conquer
arabia is that they chose not to conquer
arabia what's the point of conquering an
enormous desert where nothing grows
where there is nothing of value whether
there are some rag tag tribes
and tribes people
who have nothing to offer you what's the
point of conquering that right if you
look at the arabian peninsula
present-day saudi arabia it's just a
desert there's nothing of any value
there today of course there is value
which we have discovered recently which
is the oil
but throughout human history that was
just a wasteland it was just a desert
there was nothing of any sort of value
there so that's why these empires
chose not to waste their time effort
energy in conquering a desert they were
guaranteed not to meet any significant
resistance there from the rag deck
tribes there but there was nothing of
value there so that's why they chose not
to uh conquer this region and let me
show let me offer you a different
perspective
if you uh
see this map this is the map of the
mongol empire at its largest extent
now the red part is the mongol empire
they had essentially conquered half the
known world more than half the known
world the thing is this
they had conquered more than half of
eurasia more or less the thing is this
what is striking is what they chose not
to conquer the mongols
they chose you can see they chose for
some reason and i've given the reasons
they chose not to conquer india they
could have conquered it easily ching is
khan could have conquered india easily
the greatest richest
country in the world but he chose not to
the other thing they did not conquer
they chose not to conquer is siberia
the frozen wasteland in the northern
regions of eurasia they chose not to
conquer it because there was nothing to
gain by conquering that region it's just
an icy frozen wasteland so that uh is a
different perspective that also has the
same reasons there was nothing to
conquer there the reason for not
invading india is different entirely
different but
so i hope that offers some sort of
perspective as to why the persians also
chose not to conquer a wasteland like
like the arabian peninsula
dungar sinchohan says which is the
biggest star in the universe is is it
stephenson 218 or ui skutai the biggest
known star in the known universe is uy
skutai
which is
it has
a diameter radius if you look at the
radius of the star it is approximately
1700 times the radius radius of the sun
it's enormous it's an it's a hyper giant
star
if you look at the star and if it were
at the center of the solar system where
the sun is
then the photosphere of the star would
exceed the radius of jupiter that's how
enormous this star is uiscui
so the biggest star in the known
universe is you wise qtai
okay ganpat vagela says the government
of india has replaced the christian hymn
abide by me with a
coming out of the colonial mindset
this is just a very small baby step in
coming out of the colonial mindset the
entire governance machinery the
government system the the form of
so-called democracy we have the
education system everything is 100
colonial so we are not coming out of the
colonial mindset but yeah
you can see some signs of that happening
so we are
rejecting this uh this british colonial
christian funeral him abide by me and we
are replacing it with an urdu song
which is another
sad
tear-jerking song right so the thing is
this uh
people are saying that we are tampering
with traditions that is nonsense
traditions what is a tradition tradition
is something that comes out that emerges
from
the soil of the country from the
grassroots of the country a tradition is
something that comes from the people it
is not something that is imposed on the
people in a top-down manner
so this christian hymn abide by me which
was part of the urban tradition was
imposed on the army in a top-down manner
by the colonial masters by the foreign
occupiers of india
the soldiers who make up the indian army
come from the soil from the grassroots
of india it is not their tradition it
has nothing to do with them so it was
something that was imposed upon us
top down and it is something that has to
be rejected all foreign impositions must
be rejected and i'm glad the government
has done this
so it's a good move
adil raza says what's your take on the
tenure of manmohan singh as the prime
minister was he the is he the best
congress prime minister the country ever
had in my opinion the best congress pm
the best congress prime minister the
country has ever had is most likely pv
narasimha a man who gets no credit for
the work he did
right it is during his tenure that india
was first the economy was first opened
up liberalized and the socialistic uh
framework mechanism everything was
rejected and replaced by a more open
economy and that's where india started
coming out of the neheruvian mindset and
the nehru and rate of growth
it is clearly because india had no
option at the time india had gone
essentially bankrupt
so the world bank imf etc the western
nations they
they essentially aren't twisted india
into opening up the economy but whatever
it is
pv narasimha took the decision and he
was in my opinion most likely the best
congress prime minister we've ever had
manmohan singh was not even a real prime
minister
manmohan singh was a prime minister only
in name he was in office he was never in
power he never had any decision-making
ability
when uh foreign
heads of state would visit india he
would not be the one
uh
talking with them one to one as the head
of the nation it would be something
somebody else would take that position
and manmohan would sit in a secondary
position
in the side on the sidelines so manmohan
singh was most likely the worst prime
minister we ever had right
he was a remote controlled robot that's
what he was
be very
frank
so that's what i think of mr manmohan
singh
uh suga says on whose side is india
should be india etc on the u.s side or
the russian side
see it's like this
india should be on india's side nobody
else's side
and if our national interest converges
with the national interest of either the
us or russia then we can
work with them
to promote our shared interests
that's how the world works the us is not
on india's side or anybody's side the
u.s is only on the u.s side
the russians
are on russia's side nobody else's side
yes they will work with other nations
they will cooperate with other nations
from time to time whenever the interests
align
but your interest is always your own
interest your own national interest that
comes before everything else
there are no friendships
in geopolitics there are no friendships
in
international affairs every nation
promotes its own national interest
that's actually how it should be india
has never done that in the past but
today india does it
so india should be on india's side not
this side that side we have no friends
there are no permanent friends there are
no permanent enemies there are no
permanent partnerships there are no
permanent adversaries in geopolitics
it's all about what phase the world is
going through so right now i think india
has excellent relation has
reasonably good relations with the us in
some ways india most likely has
warmer relations still with the russians
in many ways but not the way it was
before so that's how it is it's
complicated but india is india should be
on india's side only not anybody else's
side there are no unconditional
friendships or anything in geopolitics
it's always give and take
okay we have a bunch of questions here
let's see
chaitan says why was the air chief
marshal of india
a british person until 1954 it's because
india never got its independence i have
been saying this lots of times india is
still not truly a free country india is
still a colonized country india still
doesn't have complete autonomy in its
foreign policy
india still has to bend to the will of
certain very powerful countries
and uh
it okay so so that's why the air chief
marshal of india was a british person
until 1954 and some other officials were
there until the mid 1950s or late 1950s
who were british so india was still
essentially a british occupied country
ishan says is it true that the
information bureau ib provided
intelligence about nithyananda reports
to the british intelligence after
independence do you think that they
still supply sensitive information about
our country's internal matters to the
british government
yes the information bureau and the
evidence is out now it is undeniable
evidence the indian information bureau
intelligence bureau was providing
intelligence about our guy our our great
freedom fighter nitaj about chandra bose
to the british intelligence
even after india's supposed independence
india's intelligence bureau was still
subsidiary to scotland yard was still
essentially under the control of
scotland yard in many ways
even after independence that's what
happened under the prime ministership of
sri jawaharlal
was saying that there is proof that
there was a seek there were secret
clauses
in the transfer of power agreement
between the british nehru only one close
has been made public thus far what could
be the possible secret clauses from your
point of view i cannot speculate
but it is clear that there were secret
clauses in the transfer of power
agreement india 1947 15th august was not
independence day it was dominion status
day
on 15th of august 1947 when the british
flag went down indian flag went up etc
the indian head of state was still the
king of england
that that went on until 1950 and even
after 1950 or 51 or whatever it was
india's
like like we mentioned like it is
mentioned the
the
air chief marshal of india was british
and so on and so forth our first uh
what was it called what was mounted on
the mountbatten's role he was still the
viceroy or whatever
and so on so the british
machinery governance machinery still had
its claws deep into india well after our
so-called independence
i don't know what other secret clauses
were there are all kinds of
rumors allegations
etc i without evidence i cannot
speculate in them but it is why is india
still a member of the so-called common
wealth of nations the common wealth of
nations
is a club of losers
it is a losers club it is the bunch of
nations that were occupied forcibly by
the british and whose economies and
cultures and everything was destroyed by
the british
now even the americans
were under british occupation right they
fought a war of independence and they
won their independence through violent
means
now why is the u.s not part of the
british commonwealth even though they
were also occupied by the british it's
because the americans have some
self-respect
and they are a far greater country in
all ways than the uk
but india for some reason is still a
member of the common wealth of nations
the losers club
so it is it tells you that india still
sees itself as a subsidiary in some way
to the british to the uk to the to the
british crown possibly so i don't know
what the clauses are it needs to be
whatever the clauses where they need to
be rejected
and india needs to properly become an
independent country with an independent
foreign policy independent internal
policy we still don't have that and i
don't blame the current government for
that it is a consequence of whatever
happened in the past 70 years it is the
congress policies that have led us to
the position that we are in
right
and the government of india today is
dealing with the repercussions and the
legacy of all those policies and
everything that it had been it has been
handed over in 2014.
now recently we see that uh just a
couple of days ago the statue of
navitaji swashin the bose has been put
in new delhi in rajput where the statue
of the english king used to be there
that essentially amounts in a way in a
symbolic way to a declaration of proper
independence because the west sees
subhash and rebels as a war criminal
somebody who sided with the nazis and
the japanese
right
the funny thing is the west
are even bigger war criminals the nazis
did not nuke a country
the west did that but because they won
it's all fine it's all fair so that's
nonsense india needs to look at the
world from its own perspective so baja
chandra bose
allied with the nazis and the japanese
because they were the enemies of the
occupiers of india the ones who had
destroyed india and killed more than 100
million indians
so he may have allied with germany or
japan so what he did it for india and we
need to honor that so you know these are
the things india needs to properly
decolonize india needs to properly
become an independent country it will
still take time
but we need to grow economically very
fast very
rigorously robustly and we need to grow
militarily in proportion with the
growing economy and then maybe in 10 20
years we'll become properly independent
so it's a work in progress
spywall says namaste sir please pick my
question this time did barack obama is
excuse me is barack obama really great
as he was projected to be and in his
tenure the us became a champion and
vocalism or vox did barack obama is a
mediocre person all he was good at is
talking he was good at talking he was
good at oratory he was good at giving
wonderful speeches
what did he do actually nothing
i think he's one of the most mediocre
presidents the us has ever had but he
was great at virtue signaling and
speaking that's why he's regarded as
very good and it's great or whatever
yes during his time the u.s became a
championship champion in vocalism and
all that you know the relationship
between the us media and donald trump
the u.s media is entirely almost
entirely controlled by the democratic
party there are two parties in the u.s
the republicans and the democrats the
democrats are the liberals the
republicans are the conservatives
essentially the democrats control the
media
donald trump was a republican president
he was in office he was never in power
throughout his four-year tenure as the
president of the u.s he was constantly
mercilessly
attacked assaulted abused and trolled by
the u.s media
on the behest of the of the democratic
party because the democrats control the
media the media is a paid institution in
the u.s whoever
funds the media controls the media and
gets to decide what they say so that's
how it is third why does the u.s media
love jim joe biden so much they don't
love joe biden so much they are
controlled by the democrats they are
paid to say things good they are good
about the democrats and that's why they
are positive about joe biden and we all
know what mr joe biden is like so that's
how it is that's the state of the u.s
media
rudra says do you believe in the
conspiracy theory that a few thousand
years ago india faced nuclear bomb
destruction in north india somewhere
near rajasthan present the pakistan
temporary nation which made india weak
and indians decided never to use that
sort of weapons again and to be
extremely good and kind
i will believe anything for which there
is evidence
right
you ha you can i don't believe things
based on my intuition and my feelings
and emotions
and all that
i believe something if there is evidence
for it if there is no evidence for
something i will not believe it or i
will wait until there is evidence right
is there evidence that there was any
kind of nuclear uh explosion or event in
india anywhere in india if there is
evidence where is the evidence
there is no evidence no
undeniable evidence or no
tangential evidence even of any nuclear
event in india's past anywhere
in the indian subcontinent
show me the evidence show me some place
where the asi goes with the geiger
muller counter and finds that there is
ancient residual radiation here
there is no such place
if there is i am happy to believe it in
the absence of evidence i will say there
is no such there is no evidence for this
theory
so
as of today in the absence of evidence i
do not believe these theories
all right karthik suniva says can you
please speak about the black hole of
heinz 210 galaxy recently the hubble
telescope found stars that were being
created out of this black hole so let me
explain what this is this galaxy is
about six hundred six thousand i don't
know some that sort of distance away
from earth six hundred or six thousand i
forget
give would take a magnitude of ten
orders one hour of magnitude but it's
that sort of distance away in terms of
light years from our solar system okay
now it's not a massive galaxy it's it's
what's called a dwarf galaxy it's called
a dwarf
star burst galaxy so it's a dwarf galaxy
because it's small it's tiny compared to
milky way our to compared to our galaxy
the milky way or to our neighboring
galaxy andromeda it's small heinz 210 is
a small dwarf galaxy
and it's called a starburst galaxy
because it shows an unusual unusually
high rate of star formation new stars
being born there
so recently about 10 years ago or so
they found that there is a black hole at
the center of this dwarf galaxy which is
very interesting actually and i'm not
going to why it's interesting but there
is a black hole at the center of this
galaxy even at the center of this dwarf
galaxy and it's a smallish black hole
what's the size of this black hole maybe
a million solar masses or so something
like that i don't remember exactly look
it up if you want
so it's about a million or so solar
masses roughly give or take
let's say it's a smallish black hole
it's a monster super massive black hole
like we have at the center of the milky
way or other galaxies
it's a moderately sized black hole
and what we find is that this black hole
is sucking in gas from its surrounding
regions
and when gas swirls into a black hole
sometimes or not sometimes often what
happens is that it is redirected by the
magnetic fields of the black hole and
ejected in two different directions from
the polar axis of the of the rotation
the axis of rotation of the black hole
so this gas is being ejected into the
directions from the polar regions of the
black hole at very high speeds but not
incredibly high speeds when you have a
supermassive black hole what happens is
that this gas in the form of plasma is
ejected almost at the speed of light
staggeringly high speeds stagger is
staggeringly high velocities in the case
of this heinz 2010 it is going at about
a million kilometers per hour or so it's
not very fast
right
and then this gas is being ejected and
it is colliding with other regions that
are already rich in gas
and this collision
it's like you are you have a garden hose
of water and you are
pouring the water from the hose onto a
body of water which already exists so
that's what's happening there's a big
pool of gas that's already exists in
this galaxy and this
ejected gas from the black hole is
impacting that and this interaction
between the pool of gas and the jet of
gas from the black hole is leading to a
very high rate of new of formation of
new stars
so it's not the black hole that is
creating stars
but it is the
ejection of gas from the black hole
which is interacting with other parts of
the galaxy where there is already a
large amount of gas that is creating new
stars at a very
high
rate
so that's why it's interesting this
galaxy is interesting right
so indirectly you could say that black
holes actions are contributing to the
high rate of star formation in this
galaxy that's why it's called a star
burst galaxy and it's a dwarf galaxy so
that's what i can say in in brief about
this galaxy very interesting
astrophysical uh
phenomenon look it up if you're
interested
okay
what else do we have um karthik says why
is the steady state theory and the
pulsating theory ignored
can we ever come to our conclusion about
the origin of the universe okay good
question
let's talk about the steady state theory
the pulsating i'm not very
it was once one of the major theories of
the origin of the universe so what the
steady state theory says
is that there is no
beginning or end to the universe the
universe has always been the way it is
it's always been around and yes there is
an expansion in the universe the
universe is expanding and therefore new
material new matter new mass energy is
constantly being created somehow in the
universe
and there's never going to be an end of
the universe the universe is going to
expand infinitely into the future
and it never began also that so there is
this steady state theory which was a a
major theory in the 1930s 40s 50s i'm
not sure about 30s 40s 50s
maybe even 60s for sure
uh many
prominent physicists like hermann bondi
etc were big proponents of that i
believe an indian physicist called
narliga also and fred hoyle et cetera
these guys were
uh pro proponents of this theory the
steady state theory
but today the theory is no longer
accepted as a valid theory and why is
that it's not ignoring science is not
about democracy we will give all
theories equal importance no no no no
science is not about democracy democracy
doesn't work in science science is
see it's like this
people come up with theories
there is there is a problem which there
is a question an open question what is
the origin of the universe and ultimate
fate of the universe so we have a
certain amount of data
so based on the data various scientists
physicists etc
come up with different theories that can
explain what we see
now once you formulate a theory that
theory has to
make certain predictions then it has to
match observational evidence
if it is able to match able to match the
observational evidence then the theory
seems to be valid if it is able to make
predictions that are
validated in the future then the theory
is valid
until new evidence comes up that's how
it works a theory is constantly tested
the general theory of related relativity
which was put forth into in 1915 is
still being rigorously tested even today
right
so the steady state theory says that
there is the expansion of the universe
it goes on forever and so on so forth
the big bang theory which was the rival
theory said that the universe began
as a singularity
it there was this phase of inflation
expansion
and it predicted something called cosmic
microwave background radiation which is
the after glow of the big bang and it
also predicted that it would have a
black body spectrum which i will not
explain right now you can look it up if
you're interested
the steady state theory made no such
prediction it said there would be some
kind of
background radiation but it
predicted different characteristics and
a different origin for that and when
cmbr cosmic microwave background
radiation was discovered it exactly
matched the predictions of the big bang
theory and it invalidated the steady
state theory totally
so the major
uh
impediment or or the major piece of
evidence massive piece of evidence that
completely invalidates the steady state
theory is the
existence
of the cosmic microwave background
radiation which is an isotropic and all
that but it also has these in
homogeneities
and it shows a black body spectrum and
that completely demolishes the steady
state theory and that's why people
ignore it with very good reason
science is not democratic science is
about
evidence
and the scientific method that's how it
works
the second question is can we ever come
to a conclusion about the origin of the
universe well we have a reasonably good
framework model of the origin of the
universe
the big bang theory which all which
obviously is not a complete theory there
are still many questions about it
did the universe begin as a singularity
or was there something else and
was there something before that and so
on so forth lots of questions that are
not answered but this is the best model
that we have as of today i think
as long as humanity exists
questions will exist
we are not gods we have not seen the
beginning of the universe
but what we can do is to strive to
understand to keep on making progress in
understanding the universe better so
that's what i can say
chi-ching says how are tribes formed why
are there so many tribes in the far east
region of india for instance there are
16 tribes in nagaland so let's
understand what a tribe is what is the
definition of a tribe
the word tribe is used very liberally
and very loosely these days
by historians and various people
so uh for instance they talk about the
rig vedic tribes
those were not tribes
those were not tribes you great
historians don't use the word drive for
it let me explain what a tribe is
a tribe is a small collection of
individuals a small isolated collection
of individuals who don't have a high uh
a highly developed society
that is the
official
technical definition of a tribe you can
look it up on in dictionaries and
various
sociological anthropological texts etc a
tribe is a small group of individuals
who are isolated from other societies
for a very long time and who don't have
a very highly developed society
that's what a tribe is so typically
tribes are
what the west would call primitive
societies i don't call them primitive
but that's what the western definition
is
right
so let's talk about the rig vedic tribes
those were not tribes those were clans
okay i'm just giving perspective i'll
come to the far east of india the rig
vedic so-called tribes everybody calls
them tribes they were not tribes they
were not isolated groups of individuals
those were clans a clan is an extended
family group
and
they did not have a backward rudimentary
primitive culture they had a high
civilization
so the rigvedic so-called tribes are
actually clans with the clans now when
it comes to the far east region of india
it's not just the far east of india the
so-called north east of india it's the
extended region around that so even if
you go to if you cross the boundary the
border into myanmar burma you will see
the same
system you will
for a very long time it looks like we
had these
see this is a thickly forested region
there are hills and
the himalayan foothills etc and
therefore the people who lived there
uh
they often lived in very small groups so
maybe a couple of hundred here then 30
50 kilometers hundred kilometers another
group of maybe a couple of thousand and
so on so these are tribes now like
chichen says there are 16 tribes in
nagaland i don't remember the exact
number but i'm sure she's right so if
you look at the history of these uh uh
tribes so the who are now called the
naga tribes a hundred years ago during
the british occupation of india
or maybe 150 years ago these tribes had
very specific characteristics they all
spoke different languages they could not
even understand each other's languages
they had their own customs and
traditions which were different
significantly different from the customs
and traditions of the other neighboring
tribes and they clearly had been living
in isolation more or less for a very
long time
they were obviously not on an island
like in the andaman so there was the
always the possibility of them going
to other parts of the world but it seems
like it looks like they have been there
for a very long time so
none of our great historians have done
any significant research into the
history the origins of the people
of this region especially the the
so-called naga tribes so the the word
naga is a recent
creation
i think the british who created this
word naga an umbrella umbrella term to
to
you know we bind them together into one
ethnic group they're not one at the
ethnic group they're the pankos there
they are the the mao there are the um
what are the other tribes there are lots
of different tribes there the the
marines the the
the uh
the comb
and so many so many other other tribes
if i don't remember all the names right
now i can't recall them all but they all
have the distinct culture their
indigenous culture and so on
so the reason why there are so many
tribes or isolated social groupings
communities
in the far east region of india is
because of the terrain
of the region it's because it is thickly
forested even today you will see
extensive forest station there and there
are so many hills and all it's it's
hills and valleys so it's often very
difficult to travel far
and once you find once a social
grouping finds a region that's
reasonably habitable you can do
cultivation etc uh zoom cultivation
whatever you call it the terrace farming
etc then you settle down there and you
stay there you stay put the climate is
good the soil is fertile the only thing
is you're kind of stuck there because of
the terrain and all that you know so
that's the reason why you have so many
isolated social groups or tribes in this
region of course you also had kingdoms
you had the triporis you had the maids
the manipuri the manipur was a very
was a very massive extensive kingdom it
included all of nagaland parts of burma
and so on so that's all history it's
always been ebbing and flowing
expanding and contracting the
homes the the maintains the the triporis
and so on so these were kingdoms you
could even say empires in certain points
in time but you also had all these
tribal groupings who were more or less
autonomous they had their own culture
their own rich individual indigenous
traditions and culture religion whatever
kind of it's been wiped out but that's
the kind of
history this region has seen
so that's how tribes are formed a group
of people who kind of gets isolated in a
region and for whatever reason they
don't develop a very high
uh sophisticated culture because of this
small size of the source of the social
grouping more more or less
so it's an interesting anthropological
sociological uh research topic and
phenomenon but very interesting question
that chi-ching has asked
so it's something that if you're
interested you can certainly uh delve
much deeper into
says uh what did the us what did america
do right to become a superpower and
arnold says it was the europeans who
colonized most of the world how is
america our superpower today
good question
gentlemen
understand one thing
yes it is the europeans who colonize
most of the world and among the
europeans it was the british who were
able to colonize most of the world the
biggest empire the world has ever seen
and so on so forth they call it
but today they have
shriveled up
and shrunk and they are essentially
nobodies today the uk
so what happened to all that power in
the empire
let me explain something
the british empire never really died
it reincarnated
its reincarnation is the american empire
you we see america as the paradise
paragon of democracy human rights all
that america is actually an empire
the united states is the successor
empire of the british raj of the british
empire
that's what it is
of course they will not call themselves
an empire they will talk about the rules
based international order and
democracy and human rights and liberal
values and all that nonsense
it is a nice
it's a nice covering to wear below which
you have the imperial face
so the united states is essentially an
empire today
and how do we know it's an empire we
call it superpowers these days the
united states is the sole superpower in
the world like velena chicago explained
in the previous podcast it is the only
country that qualifies to be a
superpower for two reasons first of all
their currency is the global reserve
currency the u.s dollar all the
financial institutions are controlled by
them the international monetary fund imf
the world bank and so on right
they control the entire global order the
so-called rules based global order they
control all the major institutions in
the world
and they are the only country that can
intervene militarily anywhere in the
world at half an hour's notice
or less than half an hour's notice
so that is the hallmark of an empire
so the americans
understand are an empire you can call it
a superpower you can use whatever
euphemism you want to use for it they
are the successor state of the
british empire now what did they do
right the americans are the descendants
of the british
the british
colonialists colonized the world the
colonies india massacred indians 100
million indians they plundered
everything of value out of india they
tried to do the same with china they
succeeded to us to a certain extent they
destroyed africa completely
and they did the same in australia
occu conquered and occupied the land or
stole the land from the natives they did
the same thing in new zealand and they
did the same thing in north america
and the two success two two states that
are the outcome of the british
colonization and french colonization to
some extent are the united states and
canada so what did the americans do
right first of all the thing they do i
did right was the stolen entire
continent from the natives
they massacred the natives it is
believed about 100 million american
indians or native americans may have
died
there is no evidence for these numbers
because nobody has done any research
it's supposed it is something to be kept
secret
so this tool an entire continent an
enormous land mass let's take a look at
the landmass shall we uh let me share my
screen yes one second let me
share
as always we go to a map
where's the map here's the map
okay let's remove the question
look at the size of this continent
they stole this entire continent from
the natives they marginalized killed
massacred genocided the natives
and took over the entire continent look
at the size of this country they got
this for free
they got this for free that is the first
thing they did right
right
that's the first thing the americans did
uh what is the second thing that they
did right uh
so
firstly the first step was to steal the
entire continent from the natives kill
the natives
marginalize them make them invisible the
second thing they did was
they needed to farm the land till the
land exploit the land all that now
that's hard work so what do you do you
bring in slaves to do that work for you
so
they crossed the atlantic
went to uh west africa this region here
the western sahara
mali senegal etc
the the black african countries and they
brought in shiploads of slaves in the
transatlantic slave trade
and these slaves within did all the hard
work for the americans for free
and that's how they built up this
enormous country and this huge economy
on the on the backs of the genocide of
one people
the native americans
and the enslavement of other people
the african-americans the black people
of africa
that's how they built up this enormous
country enormous economy
then in the second world war they
intervened they had so much
so many resources they intervened and
they won the second world war
and then the military-industrial complex
took over and that's what created the
u.s empire it's a long story but that
kind of explains how the americans
became a superpower in very very very
very brief
it's a long longer story than that
obviously
so it's something that you may want to
look into in detail if you if you wish
all right another question is from mona
lisa
please explain the connection between
the irish goddess danu
and the rigvedic goddess the no now the
european historians et cetera they will
say there is no connection nothing
nothing doing nothing nothing nothing
it's totally different and they try to
invent certain
etymological etymological
roots for the irish goddess dhanu that
it may uh
it may uh originate in some
proto-latin word etc but there is no
connection between india the indian
dhanu
now let's understand the real history
so in the rigveda which is the world's
oldest known literature the world's
oldest known literature and a snapshot
of the oldest known society and culture
and civilization in the world is the
rigveda in the regular there is the
mention of this
goddess
a river goddess
an asura goddess called dhanu devi dhanu
she is still worshiped in bali for
instance as a river goddess devi danu
now
so you had this goddess asura goddess
danu in the rig veda there is a
significant mentions
about this goddess in the literature in
the rigveda now she had
apparently a hundred children asuras
okay and these were the children of
dhanu the sons of danu the dhanavas
the dhanavas so the dhana was verasaurus
the gods were the
devas and there was a conflict in in in
the records between the devas and the
dhanavas of the the the devas and the
assaults
and the assaults were defeated and they
were exiled
from arya birth from from jambudvi from
india
so they were sent into exile
according to the story
and then they
uh then they are no longer mentioned so
they fade out of civilized of the of the
memory of the civilized people the
people of india
so that seems to be the end of the story
of the dhanavas
in indian literature in our literary
records but is it so
so let us go into that a little bit more
so let me share an image
now what we find is if we go and look at
the map of europe and the major rivers
of europe
if you look at that we find a whole
bunch of rivers the dawn the niger the
danube
the danube right danube knight neister
don
donets
[Music]
a whole bunch of european rivers
are named
after
this goddess after after dhanu the root
word if you look at it linguistically if
you do a proper linguistic analysis you
find that the root word
of all these european rivers which are
found in eastern and central europe the
root word of the names of all these
european rivers is dhanu
right that is curious you also find that
the word
for river
in this kitchen language is dhanu
in the
in certain other ancient languages the
word for fluid and water and drop was
also done so there's always this
connection with water in rivers
and this the fact that you find all
these european rivers
in central europe and eastern europe
that are named after the same goddess
dhanu all named after one
goddess it seems to demonstrate
a gradual westward expansion of a group
of people who somehow was who somehow
worshiped a goddess a river goddess
named dhanu and whichever new river they
encountered that they gave the name of
their goddess to the driver
and eventually the names were distorted
and that's how they became dawn danube
dyester etc today
right so it is clear that there is
a curious
pattern of a westward expansion of a
group of group of people from the east
who all worshiped a goddess called anu a
river goddess so the question is where
did these people end up
these
people who
worshipped god has done where did they
end up
this is where they ended up
so in irish mythology
the mother of the irish people is a
goddess called
who is a river goddess
again she is a river goddess the same
pattern
and the mythological ancestors of the
irish people
are called the twata de danan which
means the peoples of the goddess
dhanu now tell me this is a coincidence
anybody who says this is a coincidence
needs to have their head examined
it is clear that this demonstrates a
westward
expansion in very deep antiquity
of an ancient population of indians we
know
that such expansions have happened it is
also mentioned in the puranas etcetera
the latest later vedic texts like the
bodhiana sutra and so many other texts
it is also now demonstrated through the
science of genetics look at my podcast
with dr nirajaray
so
this tells you what was the connection
between the irish goddess dhanu and the
rig vedic goddess
which which are the same deity
the same
goddess no doubt about it
right good question
all right
balram says
how can india get into a position to
give resistance to invisible hands like
the way the chinese and the russians do
how much time it might take why is the
russian why is russia able to scare the
us and europe despite being a low
economy let's take the second question
first why is the why are the russians
able to scare
the americans in europe despite having a
small economy
well
the
economy is not the only factor when it
comes to computing calculating
national power
economy is one factor you also look at
the size of the military the capability
of the military the number of nuclear
weapons you have and the attitude
of the leadership how willing is the
leadership
to use hard power military power
russia has shown its willingness
in the past decade two decades to use
military power whenever it is needed
look at the chechnyan wars
look at the intervention in georgia look
at the intervention in crimea ukraine
they have never shied away from using
hard a heavy hand and hard military
power that's point number one and they
have a massive military machine they may
have a small economy but their military
is what is is the legacy they got from
the ussr and it's a massive
and very
powerful
military they have a very good
[Music]
uh
military uh
what do you call it military industrial
complex
they manufacture their own weapons they
don't need to import weapon systems from
abroad they manufacture everything at
home so that is a massive advantage they
have and the most massive advantage they
have is that they have the world's
largest nuclear arsenal
they have more nukes than the americans
and they have the capability
to deploy and deliver those nuclear
packages anywhere in the world
within half an hour's time
that is why the whole world is care of
the russians
and that's why the whole world
in a way respects russia for its hard
power
now the other question is how can india
get into a position to give resistance
to invisible hence
what the chinese do and the russians do
so let's look at the attitude and the
practices and the policies of the
chinese and russians do the chinese have
an education system based in english in
the english language
no do they have a legal system based on
western values
on western principles no do they have a
constitution that is based in western
values no is there governance
system
based on the western values no they have
their own way of doing things
and they are proud of it they are not
colonized the same goes for the russians
their education is in the russian medium
their system of governance is russian in
nature you may call it whatever you like
you can call it autocracy dictatorship
doesn't matter it is
based grounded in russian values in
russian history
india on the other hand is like a client
state of the us or the west
it's education system its governance
system its constitution its laws its
bureaucracy everything
is a continuation of the british raj
it's like we were never free and that's
why indian people have no confidence no
self confidence no self respect
so that's why india is in no position to
resist the invisible hand
we you may not know where the invisible
hand originates from from
but what i can tell you
is that this invisible hand speaks
english
right
so if india wants
to become truly independent
in the real sense of the world
it has to
just look at
the past 30 40 50 years of history
in china and russia and how have they
gone about doing things
they have an independent foreign policy
they have everything is independent
properly so that's what india can do
you know
russia chinese are our enemies there's
no doubt about that they want india to
be destroyed
but there is always something to learn
from your enemies learn from anybody
it is perfectly fine to learn
something of value even from your
enemies
so that's what india needs to do
all right
why are african lions and elephants
bigger than asian lions and
elephants okay
valid question
okay let me give some other examples
here um um one second let me go to
so you are right the african lion is
larger than the asian lion indian lion
and african elephants are typically
larger than
asian elephants and lions
now look at african crocodiles
you know the african crocodile for
instance is
smaller than the indian crocodile called
the garial
the garial the indian guardial crocodile
is way larger and more massive than the
african crocodile why is that
why is an indian crocodile so much
larger than the african crocodile even
if you look at the indian sea water
crocodile they call it the
indo-pacific crocodile or something it
is about it can grow to a length of
about six or seven meters that is a
massive
gigantic animal
the indian saltwater crocodile crocodile
which you find on the east coast of
india that is way more massive than the
african crocodiles now let's look at the
uh if you look at the african buffalo
when you compare that with the indian
gore
this is the indian gore
it is a massive beast
the indian gore is a truly truly massive
beast
if you look at this animal this beast
which is found in northern eastern india
etc
it stands as tall as me at
the shoulder
it is six feet tall at its shoulder can
you see how massive this beast is
this
is an absolute unit it is way more
massive than any african
buffalo
right then if you if you if you look at
various indian serpents for example the
indian cobra king cobra it dwarfs any
african snake
so you know evolution is something that
goes in a variety of directions
certain animals are larger in a certain
continent but in a different continent
some other elephants will be larger
there are so many
factors multiple factors and parameters
that go into the course of evolution of
a certain species
so in the case of some species like the
two examples you've given african
elephants and lions they are larger than
the ones that we have here but there are
so many species of animals in the indian
subcontinent they are much larger
than similar species in africa so it's
all because of the
long
history over millions of years of
evolution of a species there is no one
reason for any such thing there are
thousands of parameters that go into
evolution
so i hope that gives you some kind of
context
to this
uh question
bhuvanesh says i have one complaint you
pick questions that were answered many
times before please try to pick this
question on the future say this sir
the thing is this let me explain why you
are right you are right your your
uh observation is based in
accuracy it's it's it's accurate it's b
it's based on real data
uh the thing is this
i have taken certain questions
multiple times it is true why do i do
that
because there are new subscribers and
new viewers who come in every week
six months ago i had less than half the
subscribers i have today
and
so new subscribers have come in and they
may not have seen my past videos i have
tried my best to put hundreds of short
clips on this channel as you know
they're all there but
people may not be aware of the questions
i have answered in the past
and certain questions are
questions that everybody has
and they keep asking this question so
there are certain questions i see every
week
so some of these questions i will pick
up multiple times even in the future
because these are important questions
and
people when they ask that question i
think it deserves to be answered and
therefore based on my judgment i may
pick some questions multiple times
it may you i'm sure you are one of my uh
older viewers and i really appreciate
that so that's just an explanation of
why i pick certain questions multiple
times now let's take your question
publish um
can a living planet exist
we know about the fungi micellar network
and forests as acting as a single entity
if we extend this to the extreme is it
possible for an alien complex life to
take over an entire planet
aka the kardashev type one and act as a
single conscious entity drawing power
from its host planet score and from its
host star
see bonus we only have the example of
one planet we only know of one place
where there is life so that's the only
example that we have but if you
extrapolate the various life forms that
we find on our planet
and extrapolate it to a larger massive
space scale onto a hypothetical alien
planet then why is it it is certainly
possible
there is nothing in the rules of biology
physics chemistry etc
that would prevent such a thing from
happening so it is certainly conceivable
that a certain uh
hypothetical species
or or life form may be possibly able to
colonize an entire planet act as a
single conscious entity and draw its
energy from the molten core
of the planet and possibly even from the
energy of the host star in the form of
something maybe like photosynthesis or
something it is certainly possible there
is nothing in the
laws of nature that
would say this is impossible so yes
hypothetically it may
most likely exist somewhere in the
universe it is said by some people
that the universe is so vast that
anything you can imagine in your
imagination
most likely exists somewhere you may
never actually see an example of that in
real life because the universe is so
vast and we may we can never travel that
far or even receive information from
that far but if you can imagine
something it may actually exist
somewhere somewhere in the universe in
the vastness
of the universe
so to answer your question
yes why not it is certainly possible
hypothetically that such a thing such a
planet may exist
all right praveen says do germans
experience
an inferiority complex due to their nazi
history does it still exist
i'm not sure how many of you have read
the autobiography of arnold
schwarzenegger
you know arnold schwarzenegger right the
great hollywood actor former bodybuilder
mr universe 7 times 8 10 17 i think one
of the greatest bodybuilders of all time
one of the greatest action movie stars
in hollywood of all time and so on he
was born in austria
he grew up in austria as a teenager
as a young man he moved to the united
states eventually became a big star
there changed his nationality and so on
now if you read the autobiography of
arnold schwarzenegger it's called total
recall he speaks about this particular
thing this inferiority complex that
germans had when he was a child the
generation of his father
that was the generation that had been
beaten in the second world war they had
lost the second world war they had
participated
on behalf of the nazi side and they had
lost they were beaten they were
humiliated and there was this
sense of
the fact that we are a defeated people
and then there was also this sense of
deep shame that was imposed upon the
german people for whatever atrocities
and horrific acts the nazis had done
so that was
uh the german people were held guilty by
by
extension
you know inherited guilt there is some
marxist term in that collective guilt or
something so that was imposed upon upon
the people of germany and
nationalism
patriotism etc was taboo for a very long
time in germany i remember in 2000 which
which european cup was it football i
think it was 2006. it was finally in
2006 that the germans
the german people gathered the courage
to wave german flags when their football
team was doing quite well in the
european uh european champion you wrote
2002 or 2006 i think
when their coach was jurgen klinsmann i
think they reached the semi-finals or
something but they did very well so
that's when the first glimpses of german
patriotism were visible for the first
time in more than 50 60 years
and
and much of their history has been
denied to them i have spoken about this
several months before in the past
one of the greatest heroes uh the
freedom fighter armenius
who defeated the roman empire
in the year which year was a 1080
somewhere there
in the battle of the teutoburg forest
one of the greatest germans of all time
the liberator of germany
his story was whitewashed out of german
textbooks
so when the 2000th anniversary of this
battle came came around
in the beginning of the 21st century
just a few years ago there was no
celebration in germany because nobody
knew about this
because the german school
textbooks history textbooks college
textbooks did not mention rb news at all
so this was all suppressed and yes so
there is this
uh
sense i suppose it may still exist in
germany that they are
in some way a defeated people germany is
still under a u.s occupation by the way
so there is that also so yes it's a
complex history
and there is this uh
this sense of collective guilt that has
been imposed upon the german people
anytime a german speaks too much they
are shushed and shut down they are given
epithets like adolf and so on so this
thing is there yes
so yes the germans do experience this i
am sure i am
not the right person to speak on behalf
of the german people but i i am aware of
the fact that this is indeed a thing
okay two questions what is india's what
are india's geopolitical options if
russia attempts to invade ukraine and
nato engages against them we are wasted
deep with russia in defence and trade
deals
second question by nanda gopan
if russia invades ukraine
will the u.s sanctions that follow
severely affect india's interests
especially in the backdrop of the s 400
purchase
and if so how should we deal with russia
thereafter
the answer is very simple
how should india deal with any country
depends on india's national interest
not on the national interest of other
countries
now if the americans
squeeze india and threaten to impose
sanctions then it may affect india's
national interest
and the americans are way more powerful
than us so they could they are in a
position to do it if they want so india
has to be governed by a sense of what
its long-term national interest is and
it should do whatever it takes to
safeguard and promote india's national
interest
so hypothetically if in the coming days
weeks months the russians invade ukraine
there's a war of some sort nato engages
against them
then the americans may try to prevent
india from gaining from from
completing the
purchase of the s-400
system and they may try to impose
sanctions upon india if india refuses
and so on so this may complicate matters
i would not say that india is waste deep
with russia in defense and trade deals
we are also buying purchasing of
weaponry in other systems from the us
as you know we have purchased
the poseidon planes and so on from the
americans there's a lot of cooperation
between india and the u.s as well
so india has to see what the americans
what the american attitude is
in such a case in such an eventuality
india has to
try and
impress upon the americans
to look upon this from a larger
perspective the real enemy is not india
or russia the real enemy is china you
may have a beef or something with the
russians that is your problem but in the
long run we need to
worry about china and if you try to
prevent us from gaining from acquiring
this weapon system it's going to hurt
you also in the long run when it comes
to a future potential possible conflict
with china
so we need to impress this upon the
americans
and let's see how it goes it all depends
on the diplomacy and leadership that we
exhibit
from our side
okay this is a question by shang jina
but it is not by shanghai it is by soham
chaudhary my good friend soham choudhary
has asked this question about 700 or 800
times copy paste copy paste comments my
dear friend i requested you once please
don't spam the comments but you have
kept on doing it by creating new
accounts so i will take your question
but please saw him in the future please
do not spam the comments now this is the
reason i was not taking this question is
because i've answered this multiple
times
but let's do it one more time just
to refresh everyone's memory so the
question is
the question by soham choudhary is
why did chingish khan's descendants such
as berkey khan et cetera the successor
state of the mongol empire the il khanna
khan the golden horde etc why did they
abandon buddhism and adopt islam the
only exception is the yuan dynasty which
did not abandon buddhism
the successor state of the mongol empire
is the one dynasty and the khanate in
mongolia
the ilkhanet the chagate the golden
horde etc became turkic states in the
future they were no longer in mongolia
point number one
right
now you will find that descendants of
chinggis khan
other khans who conquered russia for
instance siberia and russian
principalities they adopted christianity
also
but if you look at mongolia today if you
look at china today there is no islam
there mongolia is almost exclusively
buddhist thing raised it's a syncretic
culture buddhism and angrism
they practice essentially
elements of both
buddhism and tangirism islam isn't
practiced by any mongol today there is a
very small tiny fractional
kazakh minority i believe who are ethnic
turks not mongolians and they those that
small little population practices islam
inside mongolia but no mongol practice
is islam
the uh
mongols who were part of the ill khan at
the chagatai khanate the golden horde
etc they intermarried with the local
turks and they
adopted their culture and religion so
the mongols were a polytheistic people
they still are a polytheistic people
polytheistic people have no aversion to
adopting
elements of other cultures they see
everything as divine that is the
hallmark of polytheism and that is the
biggest weakness of polytheism there is
too much tolerance
and too much respect for others when the
other side may not respect you back
so that's what happened in short so
these mongols went to different parts of
eurasia
in various turkic regions central asia
etc russia they adopted whatever the
local culture was
but inside mongolia there is no
foreign religion
there is
buddhism hinduism combined and the
angriest
practices of their ancestors
and in the yuan empire which is now
china
again
it is mostly uh buddhism whatever is
left of buddhism because of communism so
that is what happened
all right i hope that explains in brief
uh what the situation was like and what
happened
dungar singh johann says you have said
many times that our constitution is
nothing but a copy of the west which is
based in facts
what i have said is based in fact study
the indian constitution and study the
1935 british act that is the
template on which the indian
constitution is based
and you will see
and study the other constitutions of
other countries
in the west and you will see
so what i have said
is based in hard facts it is
you can verify it right now if you wish
right
so i have said that our constitution is
nothing but a copy of the west it has
been taken wholesale from the west and
so on but my teacher said it was a smart
move from india that we have only taken
the best part from the constitutions of
many countries
thereby making our constitution
outstanding what are your views on this
see
do you know why india is a
today nation of low standards and
mediocrity because our education imposes
low standards and mediocrity upon among
the students
the indian education system promotes
mediocrity
and destroys talent if you pour
more money into the education system of
india it is going to produce mediocrity
in larger numbers
it is a mediocre system
and our teachers
with a few exceptions maybe one or two
percent of our teachers are good
but the majority are mediocre people
they are themselves mentally colonized
they are teaching us wrong history and
they actually believe
that fake false distorted history to be
the correct history of india
they are mentally colonized then
therefore they worship the indian
constitution they don't think they
simply memorize and then they
regurgitate what they've memorized there
is no process thinking process going on
inside
some of them have it but those are very
few and far between so therefore we have
to be very careful about what our
teachers are telling us don't believe it
a teacher is not a guru
we make the big mistake of considering
our teachers to be gurus our teachers
are service providers the moment you
stop paying them your monthly fees
they're gonna stop teaching you a guru
is a guru for life they will never ask
you for money
that's a huge difference
so please stop considering your teachers
to be gurus
and stop taking everything they say
seriously
you have to go through the education
system today because you have no option
so do it get your degrees and then
forget everything you learned the real
learning starts after you're out of the
education system so please ensure that
your mind is not destroyed
with the during the time you are
forced to be part of the education
system keep your mind intact
why did the michelson morley experiment
fail the michaelson morally
succeeded in disproving the hypothesis
that there is a luminiferous ether that
permeates the universe
so the objective of the michelson-morley
experiment
was to determine whether such aluminum
for us ether exists or not so in the
18th 19th centuries etc
there was this hypothesis
there is a substance called ether
luminiferous ether that permeates the
universe interstellar space everything
and it is the medium in which light wave
propagates because light was considered
to be a wave at the time today we know
its wave particle duality photons and
all that at that time there was no
quantum mechanics so it was believed
that light is a wave and as we know if
you look at
a lake a pond etc a wave needs a medium
in which to propagate in which to travel
and therefore the problem arose if there
is vacuum in space then how does light
propagate
so this hypothesis was put forth there
is a substance called luminiferous ether
that's present across throughout the
universe
and it is this substance
in which light waves propagate so the
michelson morally experiment uh it's
more than 100 years ago it was devised
to either prove or disprove the presence
of luminiferous ether it is an
interferometer arrangement
two arms at 90 degrees and the
interference of the light waves in two
different directions will tell you
whether such a substance exists or not
and the experiment was done multiple
times i believe it was first done by
these two individuals michelson and
morley and they discovered that there is
no luminy for us ether this theory had
therefore to be rejected so it succeeded
in disproving the presence of a
luminiferous ether it was a very
successful and
uh momentous
experiment so i do not consider it to be
a failure it was a big success in my
opinion
abhishek says let's dive into a
hypothetical situation if you are made
the prime minister of the country for
five years and given the supreme power
of doing anything
what would be your five steps towards
making india our superpower please take
the question
you see this information is classified
it is supposed to be secret
information see first of all understand
this thing
the prime minister of india doesn't have
supreme powers in india
the prime minister has lots of
limitations on his or her power
india is a has of this federal structure
the prime minister cannot interfere
in the
internal matters of states for instance
uh for instance they say law and order
and security is a state subject
so there are so many limitations on the
power that the prime minister has
the prime minister's hands are bound and
tied in so many different ways the
judiciary will not let the center do
anything
the constitution the laws will not let
the center do anything the media will
try and interfere in everything so you
know what the the prime minister of the
country doesn't have supreme power to do
anything
so that is a myth
understand that
and that situation is present everywhere
you know what conspiracy theorists say
they say that when you are elected as
the president of the united states
they take you to a room
where you get the privilege of meeting
the people who really run the country
and the world
and then you do what they say
so you know that's what conspiracy
theorists say and there may be a grain
of or grain or two of truth in there
so the truth is that the prime minister
of india does not have the supreme power
of doing anything if i had the supreme
power of doing anything i would
decolonize the country i would change
the consideration the laws and so many
things i've spoken about these things
lots of times there is no secret in that
okay so
that's what i can say but please
disabuse yourselves of the notion that
the prime minister has the supreme power
in the country the prime minister has
lots of restrictions
on what he or she can do
what
is the story of the roopkund lake in the
himalayas
why is this lake full of human skeletons
what happened there so that's a very
interesting story uh this is a topic i
could have taken up with dr nirajara
there was no time for that unfortunately
maybe i'll
i will have a discussion again in the
future with him because he has worked on
this on this case
so if you go to this uh this lake in the
himalayas in the
northern part of india it's a it's a
very cold region it's it's like a small
let's see what it looks like
roopkund lake
or let me share my screen and show you
what it looks like
so as you can see this is what the lake
looks like it's a shallow indentation in
a valley
in the himalayas it's all it's typically
snow bound and frozen it may uh
it may
it's the surface is typically frozen
most of the year
but uh in summer i think it will become
the the surface becomes liquid and you
can see liquid water there and what you
find is a bunch of human skeletons there
lots and lots and lots of human
skeletons in
the vicinity of this lake
and they're still lying around
so indian scientists geneticists have
tested these skeletons and
it is found that there were two events
where people died in this region
and you if you examine the skeletons you
will find that they have uh
structural defects in the skulls
typically on the top of the skull so
this indicates
uh that there was a sudden hail storm
what is hail hail is big pieces of of
snow snowballs not snow but ice
big pieces of ice that fall from the sky
it's a
meteorolog meteorological phenomenon so
it appears there was a certain hail
storm that impacted these people they
were caught in the open
and it seems to have killed these people
and there seems to have been two events
of this happening
so one of the so they have found that if
you do the carbon dating of these of
these dead bodies the skeletons
one of these events was more than a
thousand years ago and one of these
events was about 300 or so years ago
roughly okay the exact details dates i
don't remember look it up if you want
so there were two events and both of
these events has this pattern of skull
injuries so skulls were broken there was
this heavy hill
for falling of hail which killed these
individuals
now when you do the genetic analysis you
find that the more recent event
is
a group of people who have two very
divergent ancestries one is a group of
people who have indian ancestry and one
is a group of people who foreign
ancestry greek or cyprus or something
i don't remember the exact details but
look it up
it's foreign
and these were groups of pilgrims who
were going somewhere so they were going
on a pilgrimage and they were both
caught both of these groups of people
were caught in this region in this
roopkund
lake
area and they were killed by a sudden
hail
storm
so that is in brief you can look up the
literature and the
the full story in various articles
online dr nirajaray has been involved in
this and
in the future when i have him again we
will discuss this for sure very
interesting case
um sorry if i missed pronouncing your
name unveisha bomic says uh
was ancient somaras a psychedelic drug
or something from which plant was it
derived
what was the soma ceremony in
rigvedagira please explain okay look i
am not an expert in ancient ceremonies
so i will skip that part and when it
comes to some ras there is a lot of
debate and discussion
about the identity of the plant
which was used to extract some rust so
some is one of the major themes somaras
in the rigveda
it is this plant this this drink that
gives you
essentially superpowers of some kind
before you go into battle you drink
sombras it gives you like double the
strength or something so it is something
that is extolled its virtues are
extolled it is treated as a divinity and
we even have a day of the week
in sanskrit monday
and soma is
was later considered to be the moon
so somawar is the day of the moon which
is monday
you see monday moonday
so the european tradition derives from
the sanskrit vedic tradition essentially
so som russ its identity is still not
known there are a number of hypotheses
or theories
about what it was some people say it was
some psycho psychedelic or psychoactive
substance you know what
if you get high on some psycho
psychedelic drug can you go and do
battle can you do warfare
clearly not
if you are high if you are imagining
things you can't
perform well in battle you will be
killed so it was clearly not a
psychoactive or psycho psychedelic
substance
most likely it was some kind of
performance enhancing substance
something that may increase your blood
pressure your heart rate and
it may give you an upsurge of adrenaline
or something like that for instance if
you are a gym go or you know there is
something called a pre-workout
supplement something you take 10 or 20
minutes before you go and work out it it
boosts your dr your blood pressure and
your your concentration and
the adrenaline levels and all that these
drugs these substances exist they are
all legally available even in india
so maybe somaras or the soma plant was
something that had a similar effect on
whoever consumed it
so one
theory says it was some kind of maybe
cylo cybin mushroom or something which
is available in india it grows wild
another theory says that maybe it was
the ephedra plant e-p-h-e-d-r-a
ephedra which grows in north india
kashmir and central asia etc
but the truth is we don't know
we still haven't been able to
pinpoint for sure
what
is the true
identity of the plant from which somaras
was derived
so it is known that these this plant
came in stocks long stocks and there was
this pressing ceremony from which the
juice or the russ was
extracted and that is what was drunk
and it it
it is something that warriors would
partake of before they went into battle
so that's what i can tell you about it
we still don't know what is the true
identity of the plant but it's something
that needs to be
researched and
solved you know
okay next question
keshav says the maharajah of surguja
killed thousands of tigers in his
lifetime
wasn't there any authority at the time
who could have abolished this practice
and prevented this from happening
because of this these people our nation
our national animal
became an endangered species
so this individual
the maharaja of sur gujar whatever the
hell this guy was
he is known to have killed personally
more than 1 700 tigers
i doubt if these many tigers are still
alive in india
so the truth
is that these maharajas of these
princely states they were nothing but
puppets of the british i have said this
multiple times and some people get upset
about this people take this emotionally
people take this personally
these are simply facts after 1857 every
single raja maharaja princely state that
survived and was allowed to exist was
allowed to continue existing
was allowed to continue existing only as
a puppet of the british as a servant of
the british
each of these maharajas or whoever it
was had a british political agent in
their darbar in their court and the
british political agent was their boss
and each of these princely states
extract extracted tribute and taxes from
the from their people and paid that to
the british without exception they were
all puppets
and slaves of the british
some of them
did this as a compromise so that they
could keep on doing some good for their
people
we know the maharaja of travancore the
royal family of tramancore they hid the
treasure of the travancore temple from
the british so in that case i can say
they were good people
they compromised they became
subsidiaries of the british in order to
keep serving the people in some way so
some of them were good people but this
individual the maharaja of sarguja is
one of those degenerates who killed our
own animals thousands of them so there
are many such degenerate rulers in the
princely states
who
essentially
did nothing for the country and and
harmed the country
excuse me
so yeah so i would say the majority of
these so-called princely states were
nothing but low-level puppets the true
kings and queens of india were all
killed in 1857
and whenever they destroyed a princely
state or a dynasty they would take some
some
fringe element in that dynasty in that
family and install that guy or that girl
that man or woman as the ruler that's
what the british would do that you will
see happen over and over again whether
it is manipur whether it is elsewhere
you will see a puppet ruler being
installed from the same family in order
to give it some sort of
legitimacy so yes these people they
destroyed our wildlife they killed off
our tigers our cheetahs we have not a
single cheetah left in india today
because of these people so it is
essentially a british policy you can
blame the british puppets the indians
were installed as british puppets but
overall it is the british who did this
why are there indian servants
right
okay let's take a couple more questions
um why is the chinese a new year
celebrated globally while the indian new
year is not celebrated knowing its great
benefits and all that
see
that tells you this demonstrates to you
the fact that
hard power always trumps soft power
indians
love soft power oh we have so much soft
power if you have so much soft power why
is your culture not celebrated globally
why is there so much hindu phobia across
the world
and why is china respected so much
despite everything they are doing
it's because the world respects hard
power not soft power
understand that so the answer is very
simple
chinese influence chinese hard power
economic power and military power and
the image the chinese have constructed
themselves as a powerful country
so once you fear someone respect comes
automatically
nobody fears india today
and therefore nobody celebrates indian
culture
as simple as that
stop fetishizing soft power soft power
is worthless
unless you already have a significant
amount of hard power once you have hard
power once the world fears you your soft
power will go everywhere it will be
celebrated that's how it works
rashika rashika
rashika dagar says isn't india somewhere
the reason behind the industrial
revolution in britain during the 1750s
and 1800s
because the major source of the revenue
and resources was from india absolutely
100 correct rashika
the industrial revolution was made
possible because of the plunder from
india
the british had an unlimited source
of treasure
money
gold wealth everything they wanted as
much as they wanted it was a bottomless
money pit that they had in their
possession india
and they extracted everything of value
out of india and they used that to power
the industrial revolution
so like the americans had free land
and free labor in the inter in the form
of slavery the british had this free
source of money and treasure and slaves
which is india
and they used that
to empower and enrich themselves
and that's what gave rise to the
scientific revolution and the industrial
revolution in britain and eventually it
went across two different parts of
europe
and that's how
the british became the number one
country in the world and they created
this british empire it is all on the
back
of indian treasure indian money indian
plunder so you are 100 correct india is
what powered
and funded
the scientific revolution and the
industrial revolution in britain
okay
shivan shivanch says
what is the root cause of unequal wealth
distribution in india
so if you ask your professors in
colleges and universities your marxist
professors they will say it is the
indian society the unequal castiest
brahminical patriarchal misogynistic
indian society and the horrific
inequalities that are the cause of the
unequal wealth distribution in india and
they will look at it from a certain
perspective they are all lying to you
they are inveterate liars
the root cause of unequal wealth
distribution in india is
the past 1000 years of foreign
occupation of india the foreign
occupiers were first the turks and then
the europeans essentially the british
they destroyed the foundations and the
structure of indian society
indian society
evolved over thousands of years maybe
ten thousand years maybe twenty thousand
years we don't know
we have lost the details
it's been around for at least 10 000
years now indian society evolved
organically
it is overall from the biggest
perspective from the largest perspective
a civilization
and inside this enormous civilizational
umbrella there are lots of local plural
manifestations of culture very diverse
manifestations of the same overall
culture
and society
essentially
was very much the same across india
it was democratic at the lower levels
and it had a
uh
imperial structure or or had a monarchy
system at the at the top most level
that's what we had
and there was no capitalism there was no
exploitation of the environment and
everybody
and and if you look at the gdp etc you
can say that we had very high levels of
prosperity
and all that right
and we had our own system
in which of of uh
of division of labor and all that which
has been uh
detailed exhaustively in the
arthashastra and various other texts
so what you find is there was a very
clear system of taxation 25 maximum one
quarter of everything everything else
belongs to the people and whatever tax
was uh taken by the government was used
for the welfare in the national interest
in the defense
and the culture and etc of the country
and the people
so that's how it was and you had
industries india was the first fully
urbanized fully industrialized
civilization in the world
now what happened is that these
foreigners they came up into india they
sucked out all our wealth they destroyed
the foundation and structure of indian
society they imposed various things that
came from outside they imposed all their
negativity all their barbarism on us
which is now
here to stay apparently looks like right
and
they demonized india and so on so forth
and what the british did after they
destroyed
the marathon empire what the british did
is that they created classes of
collaborators in india
if you see my previous videos you will
know who they are
and
after the transfer of power in 1947
the same people who had
benefited
from british largesse
and british preferential treatment the
people who had become rich during the
colonial era
they remained in possessions of power
and they are the ones who are still
ruling india
so all the old industrial houses all the
old all the so called old money in india
has actually stolen money from the
people of india
and that is the root cause of all the
unequal wealth distribution of in india
the british stole the land they stole
the wealth they imposed the riot ware
system that stole the land of all the
people in india
everybody in india was forced into all
their industries were destroyed their
lands were usurped by the british and
then they were forced to indulge in
subsistence farming on their own land
which was no longer their own land
and that's what caused these systematic
famines hundreds of famines at least 100
million indians were killed
systematically deliberately in these
artificially engineered famines
and some people were allowed to become
rich as long as they serve the british
crown
that is the root cause of unequal wealth
distribution in
india it's i'm telling you in very very
brief but look at the old records look
at the history it's all recorded it's
not all recorded much of it
is hidden but if you know where to look
you'll find the evidence of all of this
that's what i can say okay let's take
one last question for today
prakriti varma says is it true that the
greatest of all time goat warriors and
conquerors like chinggish khan napoleon
tutankhamun and ashoka had a phobia of
cats
good god a phobia of cats how scary
okay let's take the the the example of
chingish khan shiri chinggis khan the
great greatest conqueror of all time
and a great friend of india
if the only reliable information we have
about shri ching is khan
comes from
a text called the secret history of the
mongols it is the only authentic source
of information
about his life
that was written by the mongols by his
own family
right
if you and this is available publicly
you can look up a translation and you
can even look at the original text if
you like if you know how to read the
manga language and you will see no
mention of the word character
so there is no
record of him ever having had a phobia
of cats this man
conquered half the known world or more
than that you think he had a phobia of
anything
does it make any sense
napoleon no record of him having had any
phobia of cats
they worshipped cats in egypt
king ashok i don't know of any record of
him
the only records we have of king ashok
are from the
inscriptions
and the rock edicts
of ashok
is there is is the word cat mentioned
there no so these are all
fabrications and creations
and stories that were created and
fabricated much later on
what's the purpose of all this i have no
idea but it's it's just a joke nothing
more than that that's what i can say
all right my dear friends thank you so
much for your questions
i will end here
so we're going to continue doing this
and we're going to continue doing lots
of podcasts and tomorrow we will do
another q a session
same time
same channel tomorrow i'm going to bring
back the video chat so i'm going to
share a video link that you can use to
join the chat and i'm going to speak to
as many of you as possible take one
question each from all of you so if you
would like to appear here
and have a one-on-one uh face-to-face
interaction with me
please come tomorrow and come armed with
your best question all right thank you
so much everybody for your viewership
for your support for everything i'm very
very grateful always
thank you so much
take care and i will see you tomorrow